<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe exposition of the Lordes Prayer contained in questions and answeres: collected for the instruction of the vnlearned, by Iohn Tomkys preacher of Gods word in the towne of Shrewsburie. 1585. Seene and allowed according to her Maiesties iniunctions.</title>
            <author>Tomkys, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1585</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13808</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24109</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107535</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843234</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843234</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7949</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13808)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7949)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 586:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe exposition of the Lordes Prayer contained in questions and answeres: collected for the instruction of the vnlearned, by Iohn Tomkys preacher of Gods word in the towne of Shrewsburie. 1585. Seene and allowed according to her Maiesties iniunctions.</title>
                  <author>Tomkys, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Walde-grave, for William Ponsonbye,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1585]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: An exposition of the Lordes prayer.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A] B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7949:1"/>
            <p>A briefe <hi>Expoſition of the Lordes</hi> Prayer, contained in Queſtions <hi>and Anſweres:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Collected for the inſtruction of the <hi>vnlearned, by</hi> Iohn Tomkys <hi>Preacher of</hi> Gods <hi>Word in the Towne of</hi> Shrewesburie. 1585.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 34. verſ. 11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Come yee children and hearken vnto me: I will teach you the feare of the Lord.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Seene and allowed according to her Maieſties Iniunctions.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON; Printed by Robert Walde-grave, for <hi>William Ponſonbye.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:7949:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7949:2"/>
            <head>¶TO THE CHRISTIAN PARENTES, AND GODLYE <hi>Houſe-houlders in the towne of Shreweſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie,</hi> grace, mercie and peace, in CHRIST IESVS be multiplied.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>E haue heare publiſhed in print, in Queſtions &amp; Anſweres, (beloued in the Lord) the Summe of that expoſition of the Lords pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, which for your edifying, and the inſtruction of your families, I made more at large in forme of Catechiſing, for the Euening pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er exerciſe vppon the Sabboth dayes, in ſuche ſorte as you then hearde, and as God vouchſafed to inhable mee. It may be obiected, that many godly writers haue ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:7949:3"/> this argument verye learned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, and publiſhed the ſame to the benefite of the Church in their catechiſmes, whoſe forme, in reſpecte of the matter, it might well haue beſeemed mee to haue vſed. All this, with reuerence both of the Objectors and Wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, I acknowledge to bee moſte true. And, if I had contented mee ſelfe therewith, it woulde haue made more with myne eaſe. Not to offende theſe Wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, but to ſatisfie theſe Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, the reaſon, which moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued mee in this ſort to collect both the Queſtions and Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweres, foorth of learned Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, which more at large haue interpreted this Prayer, is this. In moſt Catechiſmes, the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is briefe, and the Aunſwere is large: So that the Childe,
<pb facs="tcp:7949:3"/> whoſe memorye is ſhort, and capacitye weake, doth hardlye at once commit ſo muche to remembraunce, and heardeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er conceiue what hee rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth. To eaſe him in the one, and to helpe him in the other, I haue indeuoured mee ſelfe to vſe breuitye in both. And yet, I muſt confeſſe, that a dutifull care to deliuer effectuallye and playne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye the full ſumme and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſenſe of euerye woorde of this moſt diuine Prayer, hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced mee ſome-tymes in the Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to lay downe more wordes, then willinglye I woulde. But how ſo euer I haue behaued mee ſelfe in Methode, ſince I haue vſed truethe and ſinceritye in matter, I truſte you will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept my good will, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue my laboure. I haue
<pb facs="tcp:7949:4"/> thought good to publiſhe this my trauel, to ſatisfy the godly deſire of ſome parentes well diſpoſed, that the copies might be multiplyed to the benefite of the youth. Howe neceſſarie it is, that we be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually exerciſed in prayer, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfould perrilles both of bodye and of ſoule, wherwith wee be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uironed, ſufficientlye ſheweth. How comfortable it is ſo to bee occupied,<note place="margin">Pſalme 81.8 &amp; 86.5.6.7.</note> GOD allowing vs to flee vnto him by prayer, in the day of our trouble,<note place="margin">Pſalm 50.15.</note> and promiſinge vs of his mercie to heare vs, and to deliuer vs forth of all our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſe, It may eaſilie by the faithful bee conceiued, Howe fruitleſſe a thinge it is, to demaund of GOD in our praier, that we ought not, or in ſuche ſorte as wee ſhould not, CHRIST ſheweth<note place="margin">Math. 6.7</note> when as hee condemneth ſuche prayers by the
<pb facs="tcp:7949:4"/> name of BABLING. Therefore, that our praiers maye be fruitefull and comfortable, CHRIST hath giuen vs this forme of praier, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the bounds whereof, the praiers of the faithfull muſt be conceiued. Now, for ſo much as your duty is, (ye Chriſtian parentes)<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.4</note> to bring vp your children in the inſtruction and information of the Lorde,<note place="margin">1 Tim 2 1.2</note> whereof praier is no meane part<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.17</note> wherin we ſhold be exerciſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually: exerciſe therfore, I beſech you in the LORDE, your families, with ſuch diligence, in theſe Queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Anſwers, that they maye therby be taught reuerently to talk with the LORDE in their praiers. Which fruit of my ſimple labors, if it may pleaſe God, that I may ſee, it wil be no ſmall incoragement vnto me, to proceed in my miniſtery, as I haue begon. God bleſſe you, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large
<pb facs="tcp:7949:5"/> his gyftes among you, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh you in his truth. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in the Lorde, Iohn Tomkys.</signed> 
               <dateline>SALOP <date>the firſt of May. 1585.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:7949:5"/>
            <head>A briefe expoſition of the <hi>Lordes prayer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Lords prayer.</note> 
               <hi>contayned in</hi> Queſtions and Anſwers.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Parent.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ay the <hi>Lordes Prayer.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Lords prayer.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>The Childe.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 6.9.</note>
                  <hi>Our Father, which art in heauen, Halowed be thy Name.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thy kingdome come. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Thy will be done euen in earth, as it is in heauen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Giue vs this day our dayly bread.</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And forgiue vs our dettes, as we alſo <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> forgiue our detters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And leade vs not into tentation, but <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> deliuer vs from euill: for thine is the kingdom, and the power, and the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for euer. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>How doe ye call <hi>this Prayer?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>Lords Prayer.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Why ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:7949:6"/>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face.</note> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Math 6.9 Luke 11.2</note>Becauſe the <hi>Lorde Ieſus</hi> taught it his diſciples.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>Of <hi>how many partes</hi> conſiſteth this prayer?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Three partes.</note>Of <hi>three, <hi>1.</hi>
                  </hi> A Preface, <hi>2.</hi> the peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>3.</hi> and a concluſion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The preface</note>Which is the <hi>Preface?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Math. 6 9 Luke 11.2</note>
                  <hi>Our father which art in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How many thinges</hi> doe we learne in the Preface?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Two thinges: <hi>1.</hi>
                  </hi> To whome we muſt pray: <hi>2.</hi> with what confidence we muſt pray.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vnto whom</hi> muſt we pray?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Exod 30 37 ieremy. 2 13 Actes 10, 26 Act 14, 14.15 Apoc. 19, 10 &amp; 22, 8, 9</note>Vnto <hi>God onely.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>VVith <hi>what confidence</hi> muſt we pray vnto him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Math, 7, 7, &amp; 21.22 Mark, 11, 24 Luke 11.9 iohn 14, 13 &amp; 16.23. iames 1.5</note>With <hi>full aſſurance</hi> that hee will heare vs, if wee pray according to his will.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>Why do we call him <hi>Father,</hi> when we pray vnto him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>Hereby we learne, <hi>1.</hi> that he <hi>loueth</hi> vs, and <hi>2.</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Eſai. 49 15 Luke 11, 11 12.13 Iohn 16 23</note> that he will <hi>heare</hi> vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>Why do we call <hi>God our</hi> Father, when we pray vnto him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:7949:6"/>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>Firſt, to aſſure our ſelues,<note place="margin">The petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Eſay 49.15</note> that hee <hi>loueth</hi> vs being his <hi>children:</hi> then to teach vs<note n="b" place="margin">1, Ioh. 1 10 12.</note> to <hi>loue</hi> one another beinge <hi>bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>Why do we mention his beeing in <hi>Heauen,</hi> when we pray vnto him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>Firſt to aſſure our ſelues,<note n="c" place="margin">Pſalm 115.3</note> that he <hi>can helpe</hi> vs: then to teache vs,<note n="d" place="margin">Math, 6.33</note> to <hi>aske</hi> thoſe thinges, which be agreeable to his nature.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>Which are the <hi>Petitions?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Petitions</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Mat 6 9.</note>
                  <hi>Hallowed be thy name.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thy kingdome come. Thy will bee <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> done euen in earth, as it is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Giue vs this day our dayly breade.</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And forgiue vs our debts, as we alſo <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> forgiue our debters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And lead vs not into temptation, but <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> deliuer vs from euill.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How many thinges</hi> doe we craue of <hi>God</hi> in generall in theſe petitions?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Two things:</hi> Firſt, thoſe things, which tende to <hi>Gods glorye,</hi> Secondlye, all things, that are <hi>neceſſarie</hi> as well for our <hi>bodies</hi> as for our <hi>ſoules.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How many petitions</hi> doth the <hi>Lordes</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7949:7"/> prayer contayne?<note place="margin">The firſt petition.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Six.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>In <hi>how many</hi> of theſe petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are we taught to pray y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>God</hi> may be glorified?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>In the <hi>three firſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which be they?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p n="1">
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 6.9.</note>
                  <hi>1. Halowed be thy name.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> 
                  <hi>2. Thy kingdome come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3. Thy will be done euen in earth, as it is heauen.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>In <hi>how many</hi> of theſe petitions are we taught to pray to <hi>God,</hi> that we may be holpen?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>In the <hi>three laſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which be they?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p n="1">
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 6.11.</note>
                  <hi>1. Giue vs this day our dayly bread.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> 
                  <hi>2. And forgiue vs our dettes, as we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo forgiue our detters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> 
                  <hi>3. And lead vs not into tentation, but deliuer vs from euill.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>Which is the <hi>firſt petition?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The firſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition.</note> 
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 6.9. Luke. 11.2.</note>
                  <hi>Hallowed be thy name.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>VVhy is this petition placed in the <hi>firſt place?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>To teach vs,<note n="d" place="margin">Math. 6.33.</note> that <hi>aboue all</hi> things we ought to ſeeke the glory of <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:7949:7"/>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>VVhat is ment by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>God?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The ſecond petition.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>That whereby his<note n="a" place="margin">Gene. 17.1. Ex d. 3.14.15 &amp; 6.3. &amp; 15.3. &amp; 34.6. Pſal. 48.11. &amp; 86.5.9.10.15.</note> 
                  <hi>nature</hi> is deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed in the Scripture.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>VVhat is it to <hi>halow</hi> or <hi>ſanctifie</hi> the name of <hi>God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Ezech. 38.16.</note>To <hi>thinke reuerently</hi> of him, and to <hi>yeeld</hi> him his <hi>due honour.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>VVhat is ment by <hi>Thy,</hi> when as we ſay:<note n="*" place="margin">Math 6.9. Luke. 11.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Halowed be thy name?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>Euen this,<note n="c" place="margin">Deut. 6.13. &amp; 10.20. &amp; 13.4. The ſecond Petition. Math 4.10. Luke. 4.8. Apoc. 19.10. &amp; 22.9.</note> that <hi>God onely</hi> is to be <hi>honoured.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>VVhich is the <hi>Second petition?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Math. 6.10. Luke. 11.2.</note>
                  <hi>Thy kingdome come.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>VVhy do we craue of <hi>God,</hi> that his kingdome may come, <hi>immediatly after</hi> we had deſired, that we might <hi>Halowe</hi> his <hi>Name?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe<note n="e" place="margin">Iohn. 3.5 6.</note> we can not halowe his name, except he <hi>raigne</hi> in vs by his holy ſpirite.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>VVhat is the <hi>kingdome</hi> of <hi>God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 2. &amp; 45. &amp; 72. Eſay. 9. Ierem 23. Colloſ. 1.13.</note>The <hi>gracious gouernement</hi> of his people both in heauen and earth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>When</hi> doth the kingdome of <hi>God come</hi> vnto vs?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>VVhen it is<note n="g" place="margin">Gene. 3.15. &amp; 22.18. Math. 4.17. Marke. 1.15.</note> 
                  <hi>1. <hi>publiſhed</hi>
                  </hi> by the worde,<note n="h" place="margin">Math. 12.22 &amp; 28.20. Marke 16.20.</note> 
                  <hi>2.</hi> builte vp by <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7949:8"/>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Ioh. 3.5. 2. Cor. 5.5, Epheſ. 1.13.14 1. Pet. 1.22.23.</note> and <hi>3. <hi>eſtabliſhed</hi>
                  </hi> by the holy <hi>ghoſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The thirde petition.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>Why do we pray, that the kingdom of <hi>God</hi> may come vnto <hi>vs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Rom 6.23 Ephe 2.1 2.3.</note>That <hi>we</hi> may be <hi>deliuered</hi> from the thraldome of <hi>Sathan.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>Vnto <hi>whom</hi> doe wee deſire that this kingdome may come?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Math 9.38</note>Euen vnto <hi>our ſelues.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>Is there any <hi>ſpeciall thing</hi> ſignified by this word, <hi>Thy,</hi> when wee ſay:<note n="d" place="margin">Math. 6.10 Luke 11.2</note> 
                  <hi>Thy kingdome?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>Yea verily: for thereby wee pray,<note n="e" place="margin">Actes. 4 29</note> that the <hi>tyranny of Antichriſt</hi> may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded,<note n="f" place="margin">Acts. 4.30</note> and that the <hi>Kingdome of God</hi> may be inlarged.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The third pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition.</note>Which is the <hi>third Petition?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Math. 6.10 Luke 11.2</note>
                  <hi>Thy will be done euen in earth as it is in heauen.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>Why is this petition placed in the <hi>third place?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Iohn. 8:47</note>Becauſe <hi>God</hi> doth then raigne in vs, <hi>when we ſubmit our ſelues to his will.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>What doth this worde <hi>Thy, <hi>import,</hi>
                  </hi> when we ſay:<note n="i" place="margin">Math. 6, 10 Luke 11 2</note> 
                  <hi>Thy will be done?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>Euen this much: that <hi>Gods will,</hi> and <hi>not ours</hi> be done.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:7949:8"/>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>Why do we pray <hi>in that manner?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe<note n="a" place="margin">Pſalme, 51, 2 Epheſ, 1, 5</note> 
                  <hi>his will is good,</hi> but<note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 6, 5</note> 
                  <hi>our will is euill.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How many wayes</hi> is the will of <hi>God</hi> conſidered in the ſcripture?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Two wayes:</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Eſay 46.9 10, 11, pſa, 33 11 &amp; 115, 3</note> 
                  <hi>1.</hi> as it is ſecret,<note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 1, 18. 1 Pet, 1, 10<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 11, 12. 2. pet, 1, 20, 21. 2, Tim 3.16, 17.</note> 
                  <hi>2.</hi> as it is reuealed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>In <hi>whether ſence,</hi> is it taken in this petition?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Eph, 4, 11, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>In the <hi>latter ſenſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>In praying, that <hi>Gods will</hi> bee done, what do we deſire?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>1.</hi> That<note n="f" place="margin">iohn 6, 40</note> we may be <hi>ſaued</hi> by his Sonne <hi>Ieſus Chriſt, 2.</hi> that wee<note n="g" place="margin">1, Cor, 6, 19, 20. 1, theſ, 4, 3 epheſ, 1, 4,</note> may <hi>ſerue</hi> him, <hi>3</hi> and that we<note n="h" place="margin">2 Tim, 2, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 12. Heb. 12 Act, 14, 22</note> may be <hi>made like</hi> the image of his ſonne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>In <hi>what manner</hi> doe wee praye, that <hi>Gods</hi> will be done vpon earth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>Euen in ſuch manner<note n="i" place="margin">Math, 6.10 Luke. 11, 2</note> 
                  <hi>as it is in heauen.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>And <hi>how is that?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Dan 7, 10 Luke 15 10 Heb, 1, 7 Pſal, 34, 8</note>In <hi>moſt dutifull manner,</hi> and with <hi>all obedience?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why</hi> doe wee praye that <hi>Gods</hi> will be done in <hi>Earth?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Pſal, 24, 1</note>Becauſe hee is <hi>Lord of the earth alſo,</hi> where his will ſhoulde be knowne
<pb facs="tcp:7949:9"/> and obayed.<note place="margin">The fourth petition.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The fourth Petition.</note>VVhich is the <hi>Fourth petition?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Math 6.11. Luke. 11.3.</note>
                  <hi>Giue vs this day our daily bread</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>Why is this petition the <hi>Firſt</hi> of thoſe, wherein we craue of <hi>God</hi> thinges neceſſary for our ſuſtenaunce?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe it is conuenient, that we craue our findyng at <hi>Gods</hi> handes,<note n="b" place="margin">Deut. 8.3. Math. 4.4. Luke. 4.4.</note> 
                  <hi>of whom we do onely depend.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is mente</hi> by the name of <hi>Bread?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Gene. 3.19 Iohn. 6.51. 1. Cor. 10 3. Math. 24.45. Luke. 12 42. 2. Cor. 4.1.</note>VVhat ſo euer is neceſſary for the maintenance of <hi>our life.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>VVhy doth <hi>Chriſt</hi> vſe this worde <hi>Bread, <hi>rather than any other,</hi>
                  </hi> thereby to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifie thinges neceſſary for this preſent life?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>To admoniſhe vs<note n="d" place="margin">3. Reg. 13.8. &amp; 4. Reg. 4 8. Num. 11.31. &amp;c. Pſal. 78.30 31</note> to <hi>liue in all ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietie.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>VVhy do we call this bread <hi>Ours, <hi>ſince God giueth it vs?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">1. Cor. 1.30.</note>Thereby we learne to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <hi>Gods goodnes,</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Gene 3.19. Epheſ. 4.28. 2. Theſ. 3.11.12.</note> and alſo to <hi>labour</hi> truly to get our liuyng.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>VVhy do we call it our <hi>Dayly</hi> bread, &amp; deſire, that it may be giuen vs <hi>Dayly?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>Thereby we learne<note n="g" place="margin">Luke. 11 3.</note> to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge our <hi>dayly neceſsitie,</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Math. 6.34.</note> and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb facs="tcp:7949:9"/> our ſelues with that which <hi>God</hi> vouchſafeth to beſtow vpon vs.<note place="margin">The fifth petition.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>VVhy do we pray that it may be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <hi>vs,</hi> ſpeakyng of many?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe we ought to pray<note n="a" place="margin">1. Tim. 2.1. 1. Cor. 12.12. Ephe. 1.22 23</note> for <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> as well as for our ſelues<note n="b" place="margin">2. Cor. 8.13.14.15.</note> and to <hi>helpe others,</hi> with that which <hi>God</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>VVhy do we pray to <hi>God,</hi> to giue vs all thinges needefull for vs?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>Hereby we learn <hi>1.</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Iob. 1.21.</note> 
                  <hi>that of our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues</hi> we haue nothyng, <hi>2.</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Iohn. 6.16. Ezech. 4.16. Math. 5.45. &amp; 6.25. &amp;c. Luke 12.23. 1. Pet. 5.7.</note> that <hi>God is willyng to giue vs,</hi> what ſoeuer he knoweth needefull for vs, <hi>3.</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Eſay. 1.3. The fifth pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition.</note> and that we ought to <hi>vſe his giftes to his glory.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>VVhich is the <hi>fifth petition?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Math. 6.12. Luke. 11.4.</note>
                  <hi>And forgiue vs our dettes, as we alſo forgiue our detters.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>VVhy is this petition placed <hi>next vnto thoſe that went before?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>To <hi>ſtrenghthen vs againſt Satans ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">G. 4.13.</note> which layeth our ſinnes before vs, to diſcourage vs in our prayers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>VVhy doth <hi>Chriſt</hi> teach vs<note n="h" place="margin">Math. 6.11. Luke. 11.3</note> 
                  <hi>firſt</hi> to aſke thinges neceſſary for the <hi>body,</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Math. 6.12. Luke. 11.4.</note> and <hi>then</hi> thinges needefull for the <hi>ſoule?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Math. 6.25. &amp;c. Luke. 12.22. &amp;c. 1. Pet. 5.7. Pſal. 55.23.</note>To aſſure vs, that ſince <hi>God</hi> is
<pb facs="tcp:7949:10"/> carefull for <hi>our bodies,</hi> he wil bee much more carefull for <hi>our ſoules.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why</hi> doth <hi>Chriſt</hi> teach vs,<note n="a" place="margin">Math. 6.12. Luke. 11.4.</note> to call our ſinnes <hi>debtes?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe<note n="b" place="margin">Gene. 17.4.</note> 
                  <hi>our obedience</hi> is due debt vnto <hi>God,</hi> which when we doe not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 5.23.</note> 
                  <hi>his wrath</hi> is due debt vnto vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>VVhy doth <hi>Chriſt</hi> teach <hi>all men</hi> to pray in this maner?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 51.7. Rom. 3.9. &amp;c. Iam. 3.2.</note>Becauſe <hi>all</hi> are tranſgreſſours of <hi>Gods</hi> lawes, and ought to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the ſame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>VVhy doth <hi>Chriſt</hi> teach vs to aſke <hi>God</hi> forgiuenes of our ſinnes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 32.2. Eſay. 43.25. &amp; 44.22. Marke. 2.7.</note>Becauſe to forgiue ſinnes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to <hi>God onely,</hi> vnto whome we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come debtters through our tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>Maye we receiue anye comfort, in that we be taught to <hi>aſke <hi>God</hi> forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> of our ſinnes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>Yea verely: for thereby we learne,<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 101.11.12. &amp; 130.7. Math 18.23. &amp;c.</note> that <hi>God is willing</hi> to forgiue vs our ſinnes, if we craue it in faith.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>How may it ſtande with <hi>Gods</hi> iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice <hi>freely</hi> to forgiue vs our <hi>offences,</hi> the deſert whereof is death and damnation?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:7949:10"/>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Deut. 21.23. &amp; 27.26. Eſay. 53.42. Cor. 5.21. Colloſ. 2.14.</note>Becauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> our mediatour hath <hi>made ſatisfaction</hi> to God for vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>How doth <hi>God <hi>freely</hi>
                  </hi> forgiue vs our ſinnes, ſeeing he doth many wayes <hi>puniſh</hi> vs for them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>He <hi>puniſheth</hi> vs for them in deed<note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 11.32. 1. Pet 4 17.</note> not thereby to <hi>purge</hi> vs from them, but to <hi>chastiſe</hi> vs, leaſt we ſhold delight in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>Is there not a <hi>condition</hi> added to this petition?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>Yea, euen this:<note n="c" place="margin">Math. 6.12. Luke. 11.4.</note> 
                  <hi>as we alſo forgiue our debters.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>Do we <hi>deſerue forgiuenes</hi> at <hi>Gods</hi> handes, if we forgiue them that treſpaſſe againſt vs?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>No,</hi> for then it coulde not bee truely ſayd,<note n="d" place="margin">Math. 18.27 Epheſ. 1.6.</note> that <hi>God</hi> doth <hi>freely forgiue</hi> vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why</hi> then is this condition added?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>Both to teach vs<note n="e" place="margin">Math. 18.22.35. Rom. 8.14.</note> that we ought to <hi>forgiue other,</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Math. 6.14.15.</note> and alſo to aſſure vs, that, (if wee finde our ſelues charitablye minded towardes other) <hi>God</hi> will <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue vs.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>May not the <hi>Magiſtrate puniſh ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors,</hi> notwithſtanding, that wee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue them the offences which they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit againſt vs?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:7949:11"/>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſixt petition.</note>Yes, why not?<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 13.1. &amp;c.</note> For puniſhment lawfully inflicted by the Magiſtrate, is <hi>not contrary to priuate charitie</hi> here taught.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſixt peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>Which is the <hi>ſixt petition?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Math. 6.13. Luke. 11.4.</note>
                  <hi>And lead vs not into tentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but deliuer vs from euill.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>Why is this petition placed in the <hi>laſt place?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe we <hi>can not inioy Gods giftes,</hi> which we haue prayed for, except hee vouchſafe<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 6.16.</note> to <hi>deliuer vs from the aſſaultes of Satan.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is ment</hi> by <hi>tentation,</hi> in this petition?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Math. 4.1. &amp;c. Luke. 4.1. &amp;c. 2. Cor. 11.14. 1. Pet. 5.8.</note>The <hi>craftie guiles and ſubtill aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaultes of Satan,</hi> whereby he allureth vs continually to breake <hi>Gods</hi> lawes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What do we deſire of God,</hi> when we beſeech him, <hi>that</hi> he wil <hi>not lead vs into</hi> theſe <hi>tentations?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>Herin we pray him,<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 7.23.</note> that he wil not deliuer vs vp to <hi>our owne luſtes,</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Epheſ. 2.2.</note> nor to the <hi>tyrannie of the Deuill.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>Why doth <hi>Chriſt</hi> teach vs to praye to <hi>God</hi> to deliuer vs from tentation?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>Thereby he teacheth vs<note n="g" place="margin">Epheſ. 6.10. &amp;c.</note> to <hi>flee to Gods protection</hi> in all temptations, &amp;<note n="h" place="margin">Epheſ. 6.18.</note> to
<pb facs="tcp:7949:11"/> craue ſpirituall ayde <hi>of him</hi> in the ſame.<note place="margin">The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>VVhat is that <hi>Euill,</hi> from the which we deſire <hi>God</hi> to deliuer vs?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Math. 4.1. &amp;c. Luke. 4.1. &amp;c. The Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note>The <hi>Deuill</hi> him ſelfe, <hi>Sinne,</hi> the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> the <hi>vanities</hi> of the world, and <hi>what<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoeuer. <hi>Satan</hi>
                  </hi> vſeth as an inſtrument to draw vs from obedience to <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P.</speaker>
               <p>VVhich is the <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion</hi> of the <hi>Lords</hi> prayer?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Math. 6.13.</note>
                  <hi>For thine is the kingdome, and the power, &amp; the glory for euer. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What</hi> doth this concluſion <hi>contayne?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Apoc 7.12.</note>The <hi>prayſe due vnto God,</hi> whereby we profeſſe our fayth in him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>In acknowledgyng that the <hi>king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is Gods,</hi> what do we?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>Thereby we profeſſe, that it belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to <hi>God onely,</hi> to giue vs thoſe thinges which we haue aſked,<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 22.19. &amp; 103.19.</note> becauſe <hi>he onely ruleth in heauen and earth.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>And what do we, when we confeſſe, that the <hi>Power is his alſo?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>Thereby we acknowledge, that <hi>he onely is hable</hi> to giue vs all thoſe thinges, which we haue prayed for,<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 115.3. Eſay. 14.27.</note> becauſe <hi>he onely is omnipotent.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>And what do we in acknowledging
<pb facs="tcp:7949:12"/> that the <hi>Glory is his in like maner?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>Hereby we acknowledge, that <hi>he onely is to be worſhipped, prayed vnto and prayſed,</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 115.1.</note> becauſe vnto <hi>him onely belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth glory and maiesty.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>What is ment by <hi>this Addition:</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Math. 6.13.</note> 
                  <hi>for euer.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>Hereby <hi>our faith is confirmed,</hi> and <hi>God is glorified,</hi> when we doe confeſſe,<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 102.13. &amp;. 145.13. Apoc. 7.12.</note> that <hi>his</hi> kingdome, <hi>his</hi> power, and <hi>his</hi> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry laſt, <hi>not for time, but for euerlaſting.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P</speaker>
               <p>Why do we <hi>ſhut vp</hi> this prayer with<note n="d" place="margin">Math. 6.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>C</speaker>
               <p>Thereby we doe profeſſe<note n="e" place="margin">Nehe. 8.7. 1. Cor. 14.16.</note> that we pray <hi>heartely,</hi> and that <hi>God</hi> will <hi>graunt</hi> what ſo euer we aſke according to his commaundement.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:7949:12"/>
            <head>A Prayer to be vſed as <hi>well in priuate houſes, as in the</hi> Congregation before the exerciſe of Catechiſing.</head>
            <p>O Moſt gratious God and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Father, we beſeech thee for thy ſonne our ſauiour Chriſtes ſake, ſo to bleſſe the meditations of our hearts, the words of our mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, and the attendaunce of our eares, that what ſo euer ſhall bee conceiued, ſpoken, and heard, may turne to thy glory and our edifiyng. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
